Aleksander, Irina Kunina (Zamiatin); Papers mss032
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers
1937-1978
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Aleksander, Irina
mss032
1.25 cubic ft.
The collection consists of correspondence, photographs, and manuscripts which reflect Irina Aleksander's association with a number of literary notables such as Anaïs Nin, Miroslav Krlea, Marijan and Zora Matkovi, Lon Pierre-Quint, Claude Aveline, and Evgenii Zamiatin.
Biographical History
Irina Aleksander, born in St. Petersburg, Russia (ne Irina Ephimovna Kunina), was the author of plays, film scenarios, poetry, novels and short stories, and childrens stories. She received her education in her native city and in Zagreb, Yugoslavia, where she studied law. She began writing at age seven, appeared in print at age sixteen, and participated in many literary movements in Russia. Works include her play, Pushkin; novels, Douglas Tweed; Only Facts, Sir; Bosnian Symphony; The Running Tide; and a collection of short stories, The Red Fez. Her husband, Bozidar, was a distinguished Zagreb lawyer and member of one of the richest between-the-wars Croatian families. The Aleksanders were associates of the intelligentsia. They travelled and lived in a number of countries including Russia, Yugoslavia, Germany, Poland, France, the United States, and Switzerland. They shared a wide range of intellectual interests including literature, the arts, philosophy and history.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, photographs, manuscripts, and miscellaneous materials which reflect the Aleksanders association with a number of literary notables such as Anaïs Nin, Miroslav Krlea, Marijan and Zora Matkovi, Lon Pierre-Quint, Claude Aveline, and Evgenii Zamiatin. The Zamiatin materials include a corrected Russian typescript of his novel, We, published in 1924; letters and postcards in Russian to Irina Aleksander, 192837; and typescripts of his stories, plays, film outlines, notes, and essays. Zamiatin left Russia to live and write in exile in France.
Arrangement of the Collection
[The collection has no series, arranged chronologically.]
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were purchased from Irina Aleksander by the University Libraries. 1978
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Literature; Authors, Exiled; Exiles' writings, Russian; Manuscripts; Notebooks; Correspondence; Aleksander, Irina; Zamiatin, Evgenii Ivanovich, 1884-1937; Nin, Anais, 1903-1977
- Blue 3-ring binder with 38 items of correspondence, two typed items, folder of clippings, two copies of the offprint, "Moskau Leningrad", one copy of an offprint, Undated (Box 1 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Typescript of "MH" (carbon), Undated; [142] leaves Digital Files (Box 1 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Manuscript, Epitafii, Undated; 2 p. Digital Files (Box 1 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Manuscript, Iz zapisei Tarkviniia Priska, Undated; 2 p. Digital Files (Box 1 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Manuscript, Bich Bozhii, Undated; 75 p. Digital Files (Box 1 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Manuscript, Bich Bozhii / 1-i variant, Undated; 11 p. Digital Files (Box 1 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Manuscript, Le Fleau de Dieu: synopsis du film par Eug. Zamiatine [in French], Undated; 9 p. Digital Files (Box 1 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Manuscript, Atilla, Undated; 50 p. Digital Files (Box 1 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Manuscript, Untitled. Text begins: Ikh bylo semnadtsat': burgund, gerul, vestgot, kalendonets, Undated; 29 p. Digital Files (Box 1 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Manuscript, Der Floh: ein Spiel in vier Akten, von Jewgenij Zamjatin [Expose, in German], Undated; 7 p. Digital Files (Box 1 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Manuscript, Rozhdenie Ivana: p'esa v 7-mi kartinakh [outline of acts], Undated; 4 p. Digital Files (Box 1 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Manuscript, Bog, Undated; 2 p. Digital Files (Box 1 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Manuscript, Lev, Undated; 4 p. Digital Files (Box 1 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Manuscript, Aprel', Undated; 7 p. Digital Files (Box 1 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Manuscript, Sovetskie deti, Undated; 3 p. Digital Files (Box 1 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Manuscript, Lettres russes [in French], Undated; 3 p. Digital Files (Box 1 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Manuscript, Moskva-Peterburg, Undated; 9 p. Digital Files (Box 1 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Manuscript, Anatol' Frans: nekrolog, Undated; 1 p. Digital Files (Box 1 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Manuscript, O literature, revoliutsii i entropii, Undated; 6 p. Digital Files (Box 1 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Manuscript, Rasskaz o samom glavnom, Undated; 25 p. Digital Files (Box 1 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Notebook of photographs and miscellaneous items relating to Anaïs Nin and correspondence between Irina Aleksander-Kunina and Anaïs Nin, 1943-1977 (Box 2 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Notebook containing correspondence, photographs, and miscellaneous items related to Lon Pierre-Quint (pseudonym of Lopold Lon Steindecker), Jean-Pierre Selz (nephew of Steindecker), and Gina Lombroso-Ferrero, 1938-1958 (Box 2 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Notebook of correspondence between Mme. Aleksander and Claude Aveline, also with Pierre Vorms, 1939-1968 (Box 2 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Notebook of correspondence with numerous friends such as Leo Gershoy, John Hersey, Howard Fast, William Shirer, John Scott, Maurice Sandoz, Peter Viereck, and Bernard Guerney, 1944-1978 (Box 2 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Notebook of correspondence with numerous friends such as Rastko Petrovi, Mitzi and Ervin inko, Vojin Jelic, Marijan and Zora Matkovic, and J. Prout, 1937-1968 (Box 2 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Notebook of correspondence, photographs and miscellaneous materials relating to Miroslav Krlea and Marko Ristic, 1938-1978 (Box 2 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Typescript of poems by Rikki Jaipal, Undated (Box 3 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Folder of signed woodcuts, Undated (Box 3 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Record album Anaïs Nin, Let Me Read You My Own Stories as the Storytellers of Old, Undated (Box 3 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Record album in Russian, Undated (Box 3 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Portfolio poem Cook by Roy Fisher, with an original print by Ronald King, Undated (Box 3 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Chart of Russian characters, Undated (Box 3 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Naa Borba: 12 linorezov by Nikolaj Pirnat, 1944 (Box 3 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Domovi. Jece. Gozdovi. Na pragu svobode jeseni, 1944 (Box 3 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Kroz Narodno-Oslobodilacku Borbu: 16 linoreza by Branka Kovacevica, 1944 (Box 3 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Branko Kovacevic. Exhibition catalog, 1971 March 22-April 30 (Box 3 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Iz Mape U: nedovrena mapa linoreza by Marijan Detoni, 1941-1942 (Box 3 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Mi Pamtimo: 16 listova iz mape by Vanja Radaus, Undated (Box 3 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))
- Three Sisters Anton Chekhov. Poster, Undated (Box 3 (Irina Kunina Aleksander Papers))